<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from an absent lord to one of his friends in the convention</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43389</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27376827</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27376827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110093</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from an absent lord to one of his friends in the convention</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>"At ---- 20th. April 1689"--p. 4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110093:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER from an Abſent LORD to one of his FRIENDS in the Convention.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you ſeem ſurpriz'd that I anſwered not the Letter in which your Lp. ſo earneſtly preſt to ſee me at <hi>London</hi> and at the Convention, in my place in the Houſe of Peers: you will undoubtedly be more ſurpriz'd to underſtand now, that the Letter from the Houſe which I have received as well as the reſt of the Lords, who ſtay in the Country, wrought no more upon me, than the many reaſons alledged by your Lp. To deal ingenuouſly, I will freely tell you, that it abſolutely confirm'd me in my former Reſolution to tarry at Home, and have nothing to do with your Aſſembly, ſtrongly ſuſpecting that we were ſent for, only for Forms ſake, and that nothing was fear'd more, than a full Houſe of Lords; for your Lp. (I ſuppoſe) will agree with me, that, if we had all come up, you would not have been able to carry every thing according to the Pleaſure of your new King, ſince the Vote of the Houſe of Commons prevailing with much adoe by bare two or three Voices, he was forced to make uſe of Threats and Promiſes to gain eight or ten more to paſs it. You will eaſily believe that I and the greateſt part of thoſe who remain in the Country, would not have Voted on that ſide: And therefore I leave it with you to judge whether your ſelf and ſome ſixty more, who Voted with you could have carried it againſt above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty who have had no hand in your Doings: Wherefore I could not but perceive, that when they made Letters be written to us in the Name of the Upper-houſe, and engaged our particular Friends to urge our repair to <hi>London,</hi> they mock'd both them and us, and feared nothing ſo much as to ſee all the Peers of the Kingdom aſſembled. For then, reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo extravagant, and ſo contrary to the good of the Nation, as have been taken, would never have paſt. I pardon thoſe of meaner extraction, as — who being ſenſible they were the firſt of their Race honoured with the Title of Lord, and made equal to thoſe in whoſe Families heretofore they would have been glad to have liv'd, were the moſt eager to give the full ſwing to their new Honour, which they have ſo ill acknowledged from the King who gave it. I likewiſe Pardon the Lords, — whom the uneaſineſs of their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has caſt into the wrong ſide, and thoſe who have been drawn in, they themſelves, as it often happens among us, not well knowing why. But I muſt confeſs I underſtand not how divers others, no ways ſubject to the ſame temptations, could be tainted with Baſeneſs enough, to engage in an attempt ſo black and abominable as it is, to renounce the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which by Nature and Oath they owe to a lawful King only, to become Slaves to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis likely another would tell me I ſpeak like a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and an Advocate for <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> but you well know that I am of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that I have been ſo little employed in publick Matters, and ſo little Favoured, ſince the death of His late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that I am not liable to the ſuſpicion of Partiality. 'Tis true, I have not only unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd, but ſometimes prais'd the Kings zeal to favour his <hi>Papiſts</hi> as much as he could, for I always thought, and ſo, to your knowledge did many of our Friends, that the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> had nothing to fear, and that the noiſy Deſigns to deſtroy it were no more than imaginary. I was always perſuaded, and ſtill am, that more improper means to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <hi>Popery</hi> could not be taken, then thoſe which were; and ſo it would never ſink into my Head that there was any harm towards <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in all thoſe Alarms which ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many Religious <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who by their own Fears, and the Artifice of thoſe who care not one pin for Religion, have been dipt in the preſent doings, of which I doubt, we ſhall not ſee an end ſo ſoon. Pray, my Lord, could a Man of ſenſe be alarmed at an Embaſſy to <hi>Rome</hi> when we knew the Ambaſſador ſo well as we did? And knew the firſt thing he did at <hi>Rome,</hi> was to fall out with good Cardinal <hi>Howard,</hi> and all that were able to inſtruct him in what might conduce to his purpoſe? Nuncio <hi>Dada</hi> too was a likely man to endanger the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I for my part, could never believe otherwiſe, but that he dreamt more of a Red Cap, than making Converts. Had he been put to defend his Religion againſt our Biſhops, in what a caſe would he have been, whoſe Divinity ſtretcht no farther, then to exclaim per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually againſt, and <hi>all to be Heretick</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> often to the Scandal, and ſometimes Laughter of the Company, eſpecially when he would take upon him to play the Doctor: To my thinking moſt of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were much diſcontented and ſlighted him among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, at leaſt ſome have told me, that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf was ill ſatisfied with him, and would recall him, but ſince he did it not, it muſt needs be that he either ill underſtood the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> or cared little for them. However it be theſe are the only hands, through
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110093:2"/>which paſt all the Traffick betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof the one brought as bad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations from thence, as the other ſent from hence: And we may conclude, that the the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of the two Churches were poſſible, it would never be, by the Politicks of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, or Learning of the Nuncío.</p>
            <p>I hear what is ſaid of the Kings diſpenſing with the Teſt, his employing and advancing <hi>Papiſts</hi> to very conſiderable Places; his filling his Army with them, and his deſign of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing our Religion and Liberty by them; and I know how much it has been, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this laſt twelve Months to heighten theſe things and fright us all. To ſay the Truth, I muſt acknowledge I was my ſelf for ſometime of the number of thoſe who believed there might be ſomething in it: But it is now but too plain, that there was nothing. For had the King taken ſuch Meaſures for ſuch a purpoſe, he had not been ſo ſhamefully betrayed, whereas truſting to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> he has hardly found a Man who would venture his Life for Him. In good Faith, my Lord, the injury we have done our Religion, grieves me ſtrangely. For what Prince will ever truſt us more, when all the Declarations of our Church and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, our Oaths, and whatever is moſt Sacred among Men, bind us no longer then we think ſit? Our Biſhops and Clergy as often as they Preach againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> and reproach the inconſiſtancy of their Doctrine with the Duty of Subjects to their Soveraign, are ſure to meet with an Anſwer; and I fancy there will fine Comments be made on a <hi>Coronation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the Dean of <hi>Canterbury's</hi> Letter to my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I confeſs to you I know not what to ſay, ſave that all good <hi>Proteſtants</hi> will look upon thoſe who have hurried your Convention into ſuch Extremities, as <hi>Rebels,</hi> inſenſible of Religion or Law, and that as excuſable as many honeſt diſſenting Men among the Commons may be, the reſt will not be reckoned among the true Children of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor of her Communion. I am thinking to write of this matter to a Biſhop a Learned and an Honeſt Man, tho I believe I know his mind by my own before hand. If the <hi>Yeas</hi> among you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged reaſons of weight enough to ſilence all the ſcruples, which the Caſe muſt needs raiſe, you will much oblige me to acquaint me with them. For I declare to you, that as little as I pretend to Learning, I fancy I am Schollar enough to be pretty well aſſured there was none to be alleadged able to ſatisfy a Man who has never ſo little ſmack of the Duty of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but ſtrangely perſuade my ſelf there Votes were grounded upon the deteſtable maximes of <hi>Doleman;</hi> and <hi>Buchanan, Knox, Goodwin, Milton,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Saints, whoſe Books, as often as they have been forbidden and condemned by the Parliaments and Church of <hi>England,</hi> I expect ſhould now be Re-printed by order of the Convention, not that I believe the leading Gentlemen troubled themſelves at this time much with ſcruples: There is no better remedy againſt the Diſeaſe, than that Fanatical ſpirit which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in your Aſſembly, chiefly in the Houſe of Commons, made up for the moſt part of Non-Conformiſt <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who by the Laws of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and later Statutes ought to have been excluded. But let your new King alone for that matter, let him once be but ſteady in his Throne, he will quickly bring in more Chriſtian Principles among you: Tho my Lords the Biſhops, I am perſuaded, will be the firſt Reformed, according to the primitive Apoſtolick Pattern, and being eaſed of the heavy load of uſeleſs Riches, and worldly Honours, reduced, according to my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s wiſh, to a Penſion of bare 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per Annum;</hi> ſome of them, to my grief, deſerve it but too well, and if I ſhould reſolve to make one amongſt you, I will not anſwer I ſhall Vote againſt it. But I declare to you, I ſhall concur in nothing elſe, and it ſhall be no fault of mine if thoſe Lords with whom I have any credit; joyn not to undoe all you have done as ſoon, as the Nation, which I hope it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, ſhall open its Eyes and become ſenſible of the infamy which your Convention has thrown upon it.</p>
            <p>The truth is, there need no meeting for the matter. For that were to ſuppoſe ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in what you have done, whereas it has none: and is every way extravagant. You muſt needs have loſt your Wits, if you imagine we ſhall ever take the Votes of your Houſes for Laws. You will know that <hi>England</hi> acknowledges no other Law, but thoſe which are made by Lawful Authority, that is, by the King in Parliament. Search all Parliaments, ſearch all Court-Rolls, there are no other to be found. I appeal to the very Lawyers, who, after they had been of Councel to all the Seditious Men; and Conſpirators of late times, were choſen to be yours. Theſe Famous Lawyers and you your ſelves, know that no Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity but the King's alone, can call the Peers and Commons together, and you acknowledg'd it, by not daring at firſt, to take the Name of Parliament upon you. You are therefore Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened by the bare Authority of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and that Authority you gave him, tho' you had none to give him; Put caſe you had, he was incapable either to receive or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe it. For having enter'd the Kingdom in Arms, Declared againſt the King, and attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon His Sacred Perſon and Liberty; he incurred the Crime of High Treaſon, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all his Rights, Honours and Prerogatives in caſe he be a Subject; If he be not, he is a publick Enemy, and againſt whom the Nation is bound to ſtand by the King, and not to obey him under pain of High Treaſon. And yet this is the Authority by which you ſit, and which by your own confeſſion cannot make an Aſſembly, ſuch as our Laws call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And yet this notwithſtanding your Convention, which, ſtretch its Power to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110093:2"/>cannot pretend to more than Parliament Power, has done what no Lawful Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ever durſt do; Judge their King; Declar'd His forc'd Retreat, to be an Abdication of the Government, and the Throne Vacant; and finally, diſpos'd of it to the uſe of P. of <hi>Orange.</hi> I beſeech you, ſend me word what Preſidents your Learned Councel brought for theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves. Thoſe of the <hi>Spencers</hi> and other Traytors of thoſe times? or thoſe of <hi>Cromwel?</hi> I know none elſe who maintained, that as often as a King Governs not according to Law, his Subjects may take Arms and compel him to it. But you know all Parliaments have placed this caſe amongſt Crimes of High Treaſon.</p>
            <p>The truth is, you have bethought your ſelves of a ſubtile expedient, which I expect ſhould be clapt for a colour upon your Proceedings, <hi>viz.</hi> that you did not vacate the Throne, but only fill'd it when it was vacant. But in good faith this is to top upon a whole Nation with your falſe diſtinctions. In virtue of what Law I beſeech you, could you declare the Throne vacant? can a parcel of Seditious Men, met at the tumultuous call of an Uſurper, give ſentence in ſuch a cauſe? Is the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> Elective? and is there any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſted Preſident to be found, which Authorizes the People to diſpoſe of the Crown, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it Vacant? can an Heriditary Kingdom become Vacant otherwiſe than by the Death of the Lawful Occupant? This way perhaps your new King might have made it Vacant; but tho' it were, is there no Heir? The Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> for whoſe Birth all <hi>England,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> himſelf ſo ſolemnly Congratulated with his Father, is He no longer in the World? And is He not conſiderable enough to be thought of? His age is not capable of breaking the <hi>Original Contract,</hi> which you have fancy'd between King and People, and therefore the Throne, if it be Vacant, muſt belong to Him. I know the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would make a Counterfeit of Him, and this becomes his Conſcience. But tell me in yours, whether all theſe impotently malicious ſurmiſes, which are ſpread by his Emiſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys, be not palpably ſhameful? So ſhameful, that he has not yet ventur'd to preſs you, as great an Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as he has among you, to come to a Declaration in that point. It is reſerved it ſeems to your Parliament in which <hi>Oates</hi> and his Brethren of the Poſt, will ſwear ſome miſhappen Oath for <hi>Burnet</hi> to lick over, and you upon their credit enact him ſuppoſitions, in virtue of ſome new Law which ſhall reach backwards, as, <hi>That the Queens of</hi> England <hi>(to purpoſe) ſhall be no where validly Delivered, but in the</hi> Banquetting-Houſe, <hi>both Houſes of Parliament preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will ſay nothing of your Grievances, as <hi>much more cry than wool as there is in them.</hi> But I will ſtop a little at the New Oathes, which you ſubſtitute in place of thoſe which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Law. You, my Lord have taken the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance, Supreamacy,</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> as well as your Neighbours. Do you believe thoſe Oaths oblig'd you to perform what you ſwore, and ty'd you to the King to whom you ſwore, or do you not? In likelyhood you do not, ſince thoſe Oaths notwithſtanding, you thought your ſelf free to take up Arms againſt your King, and to joyn with His Enemies: of neceſſity then, you muſt either be Perjur'd, or believe there is no regard to be had to Oaths, as indeed you were no Slaves to yours. We muſt be confident Men to reproach the <hi>Papiſts</hi> longer with their Lyes and their Equivocations, (to which abundance of them are no greater Friends than we) when your Convention not only teaches, but orders us to make ſuch <hi>May-Games</hi> of our Oaths. Beſides they were Enacted by Parliament, the bare diſpenſing with which, in favour of <hi>Papists,</hi> is a principal part of your Out-cry againſt His Majeſty; with what face can you take them quite away, and pop in others in their room, you who by changing your Convention into a Parliament, acknowledge you have not the Authority of a Parliament? How could you do, what you make a Crime in the King, who at worſt has an Authority, which you have not? Zeal, I ſuppoſe, for <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, will be pleaded for your Proceeding, and your ſtrange Votes againſt the King. And yet it would puzzle the moſt Religious Man of quirk among you to cite the Article of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, or Act concerning it, which juſtifie your Zeal. There is none which enables Subjects to diſpoſe of the Crown, in caſe their King profeſs not the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion. On the contrary, the laſt Act of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> formally deteſts the Doctrine of thoſe who teach that Subjects may take up Arms againſt their King. And tho' ſome Law had made the Profeſſion of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion neceſſary, to be King of <hi>England,</hi> it were to be underſtood of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion Eſtabliſhed by Law: yet you take the boldneſs to declare the Throne Vacant, (whatever you pretend to in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) becauſe the King is of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, and at the ſame time ſet up a Man who has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been of a Religion contrary to Law, as well as the King, ſince the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is a <hi>Proteſtant Diſsenter,</hi> for the Law is againſt <hi>Protestant Diſſenters</hi> as will as <hi>Papists.</hi> But I ſee you take upon you to do, what the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> have ſo often demanded, and no Legal Parliament yet would ever grant, to take away the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> from <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> and leave them ſtill in force againſt <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Where I ask again, what Authority you have to alter the Laws, and what pretence to Diſpenſe with them, when you fall out with the King for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing? Turn it which way you will, theſe Proceedings are unmaintainable, and as you are no Stranger to our Laws, you will I make no doubt, acknowledge that there is no ſpeaking of them and your Votes the ſame day.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110093:3"/>
            <p>And then the King is traduced with deſigning <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> when the <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> of the Convention has ſubverted more in a week, than our Kings in a hundred years. It has ſubverted the Fundamental Law of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; all that have been made for the ſecurity of Kings and the State; thoſe of Supreamacy, of Uniformity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſo many other, that there will hardly remain more, than juſt to keep <hi>Niſi prius es</hi> going. For in what concerns Criminal matters, all Laws have been laid aſide by the illegal Proceedings againſt divers <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others, Peers as well as Commons Impriſon'd againſt Law, and this at the very time in which complaint was made of bringing one into the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> who ought to have been Try'd in Parliament. Peers are priviledg'd Perſons; how then can you take upon you to Arreſt even <hi>Popiſh</hi> Peers, you who neither had the Authority, nor Name of a Parliament? The Law allows the meaneſt Man in the Nation his <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and by it his Liberty upon Bail, and yet you refuſed it to Peers. The Chancellor is the Third Man in the Kingdom, and has the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge not only of his Peerage, but of his Office, which makes the uſage he has received, Treaſon. And yet you have put and kept him in Priſon; notwithſtanding that, even tho' you had been a Lawful Parliament, all you could do, is to Addreſs to the King to puniſh him for Male-adminiſtration, if he be guilty. But I will enlarge no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon your irregular doings, whereof I do not think it poſſible to pack a greater number into one Vote. I will only tell you (that to my thinking) your Convention has outdone the long Parliament it ſelf in bare fac'd contempt of the Laws. Thoſe Seditious Paricides ſtumbled not, as you do, at the Threſhold. They demanded, and (tho' by very bad means) obtained a Parliament, They acknowledged the Kings Power when they met, they ſought, and (to his, and the whole Nations misfortune) got his conſent to an Act for not Diſolving or Proroging them, without their own conſent. They then, kept at leaſt ſome meaſures, you keep none; and they were a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, you are not. I know you ill, if you will always be content the World ſhould think ſomething better of the moſt execrable Paracides, that ever were, and take you for the leſs modeſtly wicked of the two.</p>
            <p>For what concerns your new King, he has nothing but Force to truſt to, the only thing which can ſilence the Laws and preſerve him. But I am perſuaded that you, who are his Favourites, will be the firſt to repent the truſting your Liberty in ſuch bad hands. Thoſe Brutes of <hi>Hollanders,</hi> are far from the Free-men which he found them. He perſuaded them to rid themſelves of their beſt Patriots, as he has perſuaded you to rid your ſelves of your King: and is like to make you ſenſible one day, that your great Liberty which you found, it ſeems, uneaſy, will bid fair to enſlave you. If perſuaſions will not do, there are other expedients in the World, which may, and if we will believe malicious Tongues, have been thought of, I for my part am reſolved to ſtay at home, till I ſee which way matters are like to go. Whatever you Write, I cannot but think them wondrous tottering ſtill, tho' he has appeared in his Robes, perhaps ſuſpecting, that if he had ſtay'd his Coronation day, he might never have worn them,. Between you and me, the Deſcription you make, puts me in mind of Kings in old Tapeſtry, with their Crowns and their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles always on, even in Bed. 'Tis like that day he went to Bed with his, to expoſe the <hi>Raree-Show</hi> a while longer: But let him Reign over thoſe, who find him, and his ways to their mind, happen what will, I will not taint my Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and my Credit, no not with Treaſon, if ſure to be pardoned, and the Infamy of acknowledging a Foreign Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, whoſe double Alliance to the Royal Family, is the only pretence he has to the honour of commanding us. When I take a fancy to chooſe a Maſter, I will pitch upon one of a higher rank. As my humour is, I ſhould rather, if I had been a <hi>Hollander,</hi> have obey'd the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> than a Gentleman of <hi>Germany;</hi> and being an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> will never ſubmit to a man, whoſe Nobility is no higher rais'd above mine. And this is my <hi>Reſolve upon the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to which I believe, I ſhall always adhear, let what will be offered to the contraty. As for the diſmal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, with which you threaten me, I hope they will paſs one way or other. For we live in the Land of Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where Changes happen in a moment, and always without knowing why. If they will not let me ſtay quietly at home, <hi>Ireland</hi> is not ſo far off, but that I may ſlip thither, where, as I have a Title, I declare to you before hand, that if the King call a Parliament, you are like to hear news of <hi>Dametas.</hi> I do not mean to be Deaf and Dumb there, as I have been to your Convention. Only I am troubled for my Countrey-men, whom their Titles, or other conſiderations, make anſwerable before a Parliament of <hi>Ireland.</hi> If the rigour of the Law ſhould fall upon them, they can the leſs complain, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> having ſet the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſo many examples of ſeverity, and that too in the caſe of men, who had done and ſuffered much for the King, they cannot well expect to be ſpared by the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> Theſe thoughts grieve a man who loves his Nation. But ſince all the Calamities, ſtill freſh in memory, which the laſt long Rebellion power'd upon the Kingdom, cannot extingviſh that violent Animoſity, which ſome men have againſt Lawful Princes, who can complain or wonder, if Providence permit it thoſe which are not ſo. I ſhall have at leaſt, the ſatisfaction to have had no hand in them, and will never with your diſtinction of <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de jure</hi> Kings, diſtinguiſh my ſelf into the Politick Idolatry of falling down before the Idol of the Commons, Perhaps we may one day ſee the <hi>Golden Calf</hi> bruiſed to pieces. You may dance about it in the mean time, and your <hi>Aaron</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> and ſuch <hi>Levites</hi> cry out, <hi>Theſe are thy Gods</hi> O Iſrael, <hi>which have brought thee out of the Bondage of</hi> Aegypt. This is the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who has broken in pieces the <hi>CHAINS</hi> of <hi>POPERY,</hi> and delivered you from the <hi>Slavery</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary Power.</hi> They may amuſe, and they may lull you aſleep, till you wake, much I fear, in Blood. God in his Mercy, will I hope, take pity on honeſt Men. And as to the Gentlemen of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> we may poſſibly live to ſee ſome of them led to <hi>Tyburn.</hi> Many to my knowledge did deſerve it long before the Convention, and without that Diſpenſing Power, againſt which they are now ſo eager, bid much fairer for the <hi>Halterlative</hi> than the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power, for Hanging than for Parliament Speeches. The worſt is, that nothing they have, or can do, can keep them clear of the guilt of High Treaſon, into which they have run you All; and the beſt I can wiſh you, is that our Lawful King may ſpeedily return, and bury all Faults in an Act of Oblivion, the only thing which can ſecure your Eſtates, your Honours, and your Lives. It was the Advice of Honeſt Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> to the <hi>Round-heads</hi> who came to him for Councel in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the I. They Laught at him, as you perhaps will at me. But he was found to be in the right at laſt, and ſo, I hope, ſhall I. In the mean time I intreat you that theſe matters may not ſlacken our old Friendſhip, I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At —</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>20th. April</hi> 1689</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
